Lewis and Clark Journals 1803-1806 Mss.917.3.L58
American Philosophical Society
Lewis and Clark Journals
1804-1806
Mss.917.3.L58
American Philosophical Society
30.0 Volume(s)
Meriwether Lewis and William Clark were explorers. This collection contains the manuscript journals kept by Lewis and Clark on their travels to the source of the Missouri River and across the continent to the Pacific Ocean. There are interlineations throughout by Nicholas Biddle, who published his narrative "History of the Expedition of Captains Lewis and Clark" (1814).
Clark, William, 1770-1838
Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809
Related Archival Materials note
The Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library at Yale University holds a collection of Field Maps (WA MSS 303-304).
The Missouri Historical Society holds the Merriwether Lewis Collection (A0897).
The Manuscripts Department of the APS also houses:
Journal of John Ordway, 1804-1806 ( Call no. 917.3 Or2).
Journal of Meriwether Lewis, 1803 ( Call no. 917.3 L58p).
Journal of William Clark, 1806 ( Call no. 917.3 L58cl).
Journal of William Clark, 1808 ( Call no. 917.3 L58c).
Nicholas Biddle, "Notes of queries to William Clark, with replies," 1810 ( Call no. 917.3 L58b).
Nicholas Biddle, Correspondence concerning the Lewis and Clark Expedition ( Call no. Film 1319).
Charles Willson Peale sketches of Lewis and Clark specimens (Quail, Louisiana tanager, Horned lizard, Lewis' woodpecker)( Call no. B P31).
William Lingelbach, Documents concerning the William Clark Papers discovered in 1953 ( Call no. 917.3 L58x).
Bibliography
The major editions of the journals of Lewis and Clark include:
Paul Allen, ed., History of the Expedition Under the Command of Captains Lewis and Clark: to the Sources of the Missouri, Thence Across the Rocky Mountains and Down the River Columbia to the Pacific Ocean: Performed During the Years 1804-1805-1806, 2 vols. (Philadelphia: Bradford and Inskeep, 1814). Call no.: 917.3 L58.a
Elliot Coues, ed., History of the Expedition Under the Command of Captains Lewis and Clark: to the Sources of the Missouri, Thence Across the Rocky Mountains and Down the River Columbia to the Pacific Ocean: Performed During the Years 1804-1805-1806, 4 vols. (New York: Francis P. Harper, 1893). Call no.: 917.3 L58c
Reuben G. Thwaites, ed., Original Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, 1804-1806, 8 vols. (New York: Dodd and Mead, 1904-1905). Call no.: 917.3 L582o
Gary E. Moulton, ed., The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, 11 vols. (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1983- ). Call no.: 917.3 L58j.m
Donald Jackson, ed., Letters of the Lewis and Clark Expedition, With Related Documents, 1783-1854 (Urbana, Illinois: University of Illinois Press, 1962). Call no.: 917.3 L58Lj
Patrick Gass, A Journal of the Voyages and Travels of a Corps of Discovery: Under the Command of Captain Lewis and Captain Clarke of the Army of the United States. (Philadelphia: Zadok Cramer, 1807). Call no.: 917.3 G21
Early American History Note
The Lewis and Clark Journals are among the APS's most treasured and well-known collections. MOLE contains a detailed inventory of the collection.
Existence and Location of Copies note
The journals have been microfilmed in their entirety on two reels (Film 214).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Deposited in part by Thomas Jefferson, 1817, and Nicholas Biddle, 1818; presented in part by Charles J. Biddle, 1949.
Scope and Contents note
The journals of Lewis and Clark housed at the APS constitute the major source of information on the transcontinental scientific expedition of the Corps of Discovery in 1804-1806. The bulk of the collection is comprised of 18 "codices" bound variously in red morocco leather, brown leather, or marbled-paper boards, and 12 loose leaf codices, these were kept alternately by Captains Meriwether Lewis and William Clark during their journey with the Corps of Discovery. Entries on the voyage west were made almost daily with few exceptions, though on the return voyage, there are several, occasionally substantial gaps. The collection also contains some loose pages that were not a part of the codices or that concern provenance.
Most journals include records of meteorological observations, of the geographic position of the Corps, and a narrative description of the events of the day and sights along the way. Lewis' occasionally fulsome prose contrasts with Clark's more utilitarian language, but both provide concise and often exacting descriptions of the flora and fauna, geography, and inhabitants of the western reaches of the Louisiana Territory. Both Lewis and Clark included rough sketches of items of interest, primarily plants, animals, or material goods associated with the Indians encountered. Clark was the cartographer.
The APS has digitized many of the pages from the journals. Links to available digital versions of the pages are included in the inventory. You may also view a gallery of all images here.
Native American Images note: Sixty-nine original ink sketches of maps, animals, fishes, and Native American artifacts drawn by Meriwether Lewis and William Clark from 1803-1806 in their journal notes during the Corps of Discovery’s exploration west to the Pacific Ocean. Native American artifact images include: Shoshone smoking pipe and fish weir; Mandan war hatchet and battle axe; Chinook paddle, arrow, fish hook & line, conic hat, canoes, and house; Flathead (Salish) profiles and cradleboard. All 18 bound codices and 12 loose-leaved codices are referenced in John Freeman’s Guide to Manuscripts relating to the American Indian in the Library of the American Philosophical Society, particularly Codex I (Clark) and Codex J (Lewis) contain the largest number of ethnological sketches. An inventory of illustrations is available. Also noted in Murphy Smith’s Historical American Sketches. Other related images include: the journal of Patrick Gass, Sergeant of the Corps, published in 1811, contains six black and white engravings of Oto, Missouri, Mandan and Blackfoot (Sihasapa) Indians. Of particular note, an 1807 crayon portrait of Shahaka (Grand Blanc), drawn by Charles Balthazar Julien Fevret de Saint-Memin, a Mandan chief known to Lewis and Clark at their winter camp from 1804-1805.
Arrangement note
When the journals were edited in the early 1890s, Elliot Coues placed a paper label identifying each volume on the outside of the front cover and a listing of contents inside, and he supplied interlinear annotations in red ink. Those contents listing are reproduced here.
While the primary organizational unit of the collection is the codex, the collection as a whole is divided into nine volumes, with Volumes I-V each holding multiple codices. This distinction is important as the non-codex material (Volumes VI-IX) follows the codices and requires the earlier volume numbers to maintain numerical consistency.
Biographical/Historical note
When Thomas Jefferson acceded to the Presidency in 1801, one of his great unfulfilled wishes was to see a proper scientific expedition carried overland to the Pacific. As a Congressman in 1783, he had failed to convince George Rogers Clark to explore the west, and in 1793, his plans for André Michaux fell prey to international political machinations, and several other attempts had failed at even earlier stages. But in 1801, Jefferson dusted off the basic plan he had devised for Michaux, and once again, prepared to send an exploring party to the west.
To lead his expedition, Jefferson selected his personal secretary, Meriwether Lewis, a political ally, fellow Virginian, and a rejected applicant (at the tender age of 19) for the Michaux expedition. Lewis was not the worldly savant that Jefferson was, but he was well-read, scientifically versed, wrote beautiful prose, and was experienced in wilderness life. Lewis was allowed to select his second in command, an old army friend, William Clark, with whom he had served in the Northwest Territory. Although less well-educated than Lewis, Clark was an astute observer in his own right and if his prose was less polished, he was a more conscientious diarist and a very capable cartographer. Differing in personality, the moody Lewis and solid Clark made a compatible team.
From the outset, the Lewis and Clark expedition seemed destined to enjoy a better fate than its predecessors. While Michaux had become ensnared in international rivalries after entering the field, Lewis and Clark were presented with news that the Louisiana Territory had been purchased, removing one more international hurdle to clear in an already arduous course. Although usually thought of as a scientific expedition, it was driven as much by political and commercial interests as scientific. In keeping with his Enlightened precepts, the information that Jefferson hoped to gain was practical as well as theoretical. He hoped as much to spur the extension of the fur trade further into the interior as to advance pure knowledge, and wished to determine which areas were most amenable to white settlement. On the political front, Lewis and Clark were specifically enjoined to cultivate alliances among the Indians to blunt Spanish and British influence in the region. Above all, the success of the expedition promised to aid in fulfilling what Americans thought was inevitable: extending American sovereignty from sea to sea.
Lewis left Philadelphia in the summer of 1803, and joined with Clark and a few recruits in Indiana before arriving late in the year at the staging area near St. Louis. After making final preparations, they set off on May 14, 1804, for the west, ascending the Mississippi to the mouth of the Missouri, and then westward. From North Dakota to nearly the coast, Lewis and Clark passed through lands that no Europeans had ever seen, before reaching their goal, the Pacific, in November 1805. On the return leg of their journey (begun on March 3, 1806), the two improvised an even more ambitious plan, splitting their party in two to cover more territory, before reuniting in North Dakota. They finally arrived back in St. Louis on September 23, 1806.
Today, all along the original trail, the expedition is remembered as an example of fortitude and scientific achievement. Unlike many who followed, the explorers were generally cooperative with the native peoples they encountered -- indeed, they were reliant upon them -- and on only one occasion did they resort to violence. In their descriptions of dozens of new plant and animal species, in their "ethnographic" descriptions of Native Americans, and in their invaluable maps of the region, Lewis and Clark more than justified Jefferson's confidence and truly set the stage for an American west.
Bertin, Exupère Joseph; Chinook Indians; Crayon drawings; Early National Politics; Exploration; Indians of North America; Indians of North America--Missouri; Indians of North America--Montana; Indians of North America--North Dakota; Indians of North America--Oregon; Journals (notebooks); Lewis and Clark Expedition (1804-1806); Louisiana Purchase--Discovery and exploration; Mandan Indians; Maps; Missouri Indians; Native America; Natural history; Northwest Coast Indians; Oto indians; Plains Indians; Plateau Indians; Salish Indians; Shoshoni Indians; Sihasapa Indians; Sketches.; Travel; Travel Narratives and Journals; United States--Exploring expeditions; West (U.S.)--Description and travel
- Volume I.
  - Codex A, 1 volume
    - Codex Cover, 1804 May 13-Aug. 14; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page cover)
    - Missouri distances to Big Sioux river, n.d.; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page inside front cover)
    - Memo of wintering, n.d.; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 1)
    - Memo of country, n.d.; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 2)
    - Journal, 1804 May 13-Aug. 14; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 3-179)
      - St. Charles exploration, 1804 May 14 (Page 4)
      - Manitou on a rock, 1804 June 5 (Page 34)
      - Meeting a group of Native Americans, 1804 Aug. 3 (Page 155)
    - Latitudes, n.d.; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 180-181)
    - Astronomical observations, n.d.; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 182-183)
    - Memo of badger, n.d.; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 184)
    - Astronomical observations, n.d.; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page inside back cover)
  - Codex Aa, 1 paper enclosure
    - Journal (fragment), 1804 May 20 and 15; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 1-8)
      Scope and Contents note
      Elliot Coues found this fragment fastened to the inside cover of Codex C with red sealing wax.
  - Codex B, 1 volume
    - Memo of curious bird, n.d.; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 2)
    - Journal, 1804 Aug. 15-Oct. 3; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 3-178)
      - Death of Sgt. Floyd, page 1, 1804 Aug. 20 (Page 13)
      - Death of Sgt. Floyd, page 2, 1804 Aug. 20 (Page 14)
      - Soues River, 1804 Aug. 21 (Page 15)
    - Memo of Indians and pay due men, 1804; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 2)
  - Codex Ba, 1 paper enclosure
    - Journal (fragment), 1804 Sep. 16-17; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 1-8)
      Elliot Coues found this fragment loose.
  - Codex C, 1 volume
    The volume follows normal pagination through page 214. After this, entries begin from the back and follow reverse pagination.
    - Indian memoranda, Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page inside front cover)
    - Botanical memoranda, Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 1)
    - Journal, 1804 Oct. 1-1805 Feb. 2; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 2-160)
      - War hatchet, 1805 Jan. 28-29 (Page 158)
    - Journal, 1805 Feb. 3-13; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 160-174)
      Entries during Clark's absence hunting.
      - Battle ax, 1805 Feb. 5 (Page 165)
    - Journal of hunting trip, 1805 Feb. 3-13; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 174-177)
    - Journal, 1805 Feb. 14-Mar. 21; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 178-198)
    - Journal, 1805 Mar. 16; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 199-202)
    - Journal, 1805 Mar. 22-Apr. 7; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 202-214)
      Leave Fort Mandan
    - Memoranda of British forts, Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page inside back cover)
    - Bailing invoice of sundries for Indian presents, stores, etc., Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 274-256)
      - Bailing Invoice (excerpt), ca. 1804-1805 (Page 273-272)
    - Sketch of Red River and St. Peters., [1804-1805 Winter]; 1 map, 20.3 x 12 cm; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 255)
      Other Finding Aids note
      Realms of Gold, 28 (1).
    - Summary statement of the rivers, etc., n.d.; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 253-248)
    - Distances of sundry places, St. Louis to Mandan, Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 247)
    - Weather diary, 1804 Jan. 1-1805 Apr. 7; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 248-216)
- Volume II.
  - Codex D, 1 volume
    - Journal, 1805 Apr. 7-May23; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 3-139)
      - Encounter with a grizzly bear, page 1, 1805 Apr. 29 (Page 66)
      - Encounter with a grizzly bear, page 2, 1805 Apr. 29 (Page 67)
      - Encounter with a grizzly bear, page 3, 1805 Apr. 29 (Page 68)
      - Encounter with a grizzly bear, page 4, 1805 Apr. 29 (Page 69)
      - First use of name Sah-ca-gah-wea (Sacagawea), ca. 1805 Apr.-May (Page 131)
    - Weather diary, 1805 June; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 140)
      This page is the concluding page of a weather diary for June 1805, which was written in reverse pagination at the back of the journal. Five leaves, p. 141-152 (weather diary for Apr., May, and June 1805) are torn out and are now located in Codex Fe.
  - Codex E, 1 volume
    - Journal, 1805 May 24-Jul. 16; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 1-156)
      - Draught of the falls and portage of the Missouri River, ca. 1805 Jul. 4; 1 map, 40.6 x 12 cm; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 132-133)
        Realms of Gold, 28 (2).
  - Codex F, 1 volume
    - Journal, 1805 Jul. 17-Aug. 22; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 1-154)
      - Latitude measurements and descriptions of the Missouri River, 1805 Jul. 27-28 (Page 40)
      - Shoshone smoking pipe, 1805 Aug. 13 (Page 99)
      - Lewis' contemplative entry (birthday), p.1, 1805 Aug. 18 (Page 128)
      - Lewis' contemplative entry (birthday), p.2, 1805 Aug. 18 (Page 129)
      - Lewis' contemplative entry (birthday), p.3, 1805 Aug. 18-19 (Page 130)
      - Shoshone fish weir, 1805 Aug. 21 (Page 147)
  - Codex Fa, 1 paper enclosure
    - Journal fragment, 1805 Aug. 1-4; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 1-8)
      Coues notes, "This is practically a duplicate of Aug. 1-4 in Codex F, p. 52-65, so far as Lewis' separate reconnaisance of those days is concerned. But it does not give the corresponding matter for Clark Aug. 1-4, for whom see Codex G."
  - Codex Fb, 1 paper enclosure
    - Journal fragment, 1805 Aug. 23-26; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 1-26)
      "The Shoshone fragment of Lewis' Journal. Found loose."
  - Codex Fc, 1 paper enclosure
    - Journal fragment, 1805 Sep. 9-10; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 1-4)
  - Codex Fd, 1 paper enclosure
    - Journal fragment, 1805 Sep. 18-22; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 1-8)
  - Codex Fe, 1 paper enclosure
    - Weather diary fragment, 1805 Apr.-Sep.; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 1-16)
      For remarks for June 1805, see Codex D, p. 140.
      - Hailstorm description, 1805 Jul. 6 (Page 14)
      - Diary of the weather for the month of July 1805, 1805 Jul. (Page 15)
  - Codex G, 1 volume
    - Distances and latitudes, Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 1 and fly leaf)
    - Journal, 1805 Jul. 1-Oct. 10; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 2-150)
- Volume III.
  - Codex H, 1 volume
    - Memo of maps, n.d.; Biddle, Nicholas, 1786-1844 (Page fly leaf)
    - Colored sketch of Great Falls of the Columbia River, 1805 Oct. 22-23; 1 map, 20.3 x 12.7 cm; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 1)
      Realms of Gold, 28 (3).
    - Colored sketch of Long and Short Narrows of the Columbia River, 1805 Oct. 22-28; 1 map, 40.6 x 12 cm; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 2-3)
      Realms of Gold, 28 (6).
    - Colored sketch of Great Chute of the Columbia River, 1805 Oct. 30-Nov. 2; 1 map, 20.3 x 12 cm; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 4)
      Realms of Gold, 28 (5).
    - Journal, 1805 Oct. 11-Nov. 19; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 5-152)
      - Confluence of Snake and Columbia Rivers, ca. 1805 Oct. 18; 1 map, 12 x 20.3 cm; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 33)
        Realms of Gold, 28 (4).
      - Latitude measurements and description of a river, 1805 Nov. 7-8 (Page 147)
  - Codex I, 1 volume
    The volume follows normal pagination through page 144. After this, entries begin from the back and follow reverse pagination.
    - Estimated distances from Fort Mandan to mouth of the Columbia River, Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 2-12)
      - Tongue Point, Oregon, 1805-1806 Winter (Page 11)
    - Diary of the weather, 1805 Apr.-1806 Jan.; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 13-33)
    - Journal, 1805 Nov.19 - 1806 Jan. 29; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 34-144)
      - Christmas, Wednesday 25th December, 1805, 1805 Dec. 25 (Page 76)
      - Conic hat, 1805 Dec. 29 (Page 80)
      - Arrow, 1806 Jan. 15 (Page 119)
      - Bone fishhook and line, 1806 Jan. 16 (Page 122)
      - Conic hat and double-edged knife, 1806 Jan. 29 (Page 144)
    - List of traders at mouth of Columbia River, n.d.; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 156)
    - Estimate of Western Indians, Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 155-147)
      - Mouth of the Columbia River (Cape Disappointment), 1805 Nov. 16-25; 1 map, 20.3 x 12 cm; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 152)
        Realms of Gold, 28 (7).
    - Journal fragment, 1806 Jan. 1-3; Clark, William, 1770-1838 (Page 146-145)
  - Codex Ia, 1 paper enclosure
    - Journal fragment, 1805 Nov. 29-Dec. 1; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 1-10)
      Rough notes from when Lewis left Clark near the mouth of the Columbia for a few days to examine the southwest side.
      - Point Adams, Oregon, 1805 Dec. 1; 1 map, 16.5 x 9.5 cm; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 7)
        Realms of Gold, 28 (8).
  - Codex J, 1 volume
    The volume follows normal pagination through page 145. After this, entries begin from the back and follow reverse pagination.
    - Codex Cover, 1806 Jan. 1-Mar. 20; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page cover)
    - Sketches of Indian implements, 1806 Jan. 1; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 1)
    - Journal, 1806 Jan. 1-Mar. 20; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 3-145)
      Fort Clatsop
      - Arrow, 1806 Jan. 15 (Page 25)
      - Bone fishhook and line, 1806 Jan. 16-17 (Page 28)
      - Digging instrument, 1806 Jan. 23-25 (Page 40)
      - Conic hat and double-edged knife, 1806 Jan. 29-31 (Page 48)
      - Paddle, small canoe, canoe with high bow, and most common canoe, 1806 Feb. 1 (Page 52)
      - Canoe with carved images, 1806 Feb. 1 (Page 53)
      - Elk hunting entry, 1806 Feb. 3 (Page 56)
      - Fir leaf (Pseudotsuga taxifolia, Douglas fir), 1806 Feb. 9 (Page 65)
      - Maple leaf (Acer circinatum, vine maple), 1806 Feb. 10 (Page 66)
      - Fern leaf (Polystichum munitum, Christmas fern), 1806 Feb. 13 (Page 71)
      - Head of a vulture (Gymnops californianus, California condor), 1806 Feb. 16 (Page 80)
      - Pine cone (Picea sitchensis, Sitka spruce), 1806 Feb. 18-19 (Page 83)
      - Eulachon (Thaleichthys pacificus), 1806 Feb. 24 (Page 93)
      - Head of the Cock of the Plains (Centrocerus urophasianus, sage grouse), 1806 Mar. 2-3 (Page 107)
      - Head of a white gull (Fulmarus glacialis, northern fulmar), 1806 Mar. 7 (Page 115)
      - Head of a brant (Anser albifrons, greater white-fronted goose), 1806 Mar. 15 (Page 131)
      - White salmon trout (Oncorhynchus kisutch, coho salmon), 1806 Mar. 16 (Page 133)
    - Weather diary, 1806 Jan.-Mar.; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 152-145)
      - Miscellaneous remarks for January 1806, 1806 Jan. (Page 151)
  - Codex K, 1 volume
    The volume follows normal pagination through page 147. After this, entries begin from the back and follow reverse pagination.
    - Journal, 1806 Mar. 21-May 23; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 1-147)
      - Iron scimitar, 1806 Mar. 29 (Page 14)
      - Confluence of Willamette and Columbia Rivers and environs, 1806 Apr. 3; 1 map, 20.3 x 12 cm; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 28-29)
        Realms of Gold, 28 (9).
      - Two views of a canoe, 1806 Apr. 6 (Page 33)
      - Plan of a Chinookan house, 1806 Apr. 6 (Page 39)
      - Bone fishhook, 1806 Apr. 26 (Page 83)
      - Fish net, 1806 May 18 (Page 139)
    - Weather diary, 1806 Apr.-May; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 152-147)
- Volume IV.
  - Codex L, 1 volume
    - Astronomical memo, 1806 June 9; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page flyleaf)
    - Journal, 1806 May 24-Jul. 4; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 1-80)
    - Blank, n.d.; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 81-98)
      These pages left blank by Lewis for insertion of fragment of Journal 1806 Jul. 5-14. See Codex La
    - Journal, 1806 Jul. 15-Aug. 8; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 99-144)
      Page 144 calls for a supplement. This supplement is Codex Lb
    - Weather diary, 1806 Jun.-Aug.; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 145-150)
    - Memo of Dickson and Hancock, Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page flyleaf)
  - Codex La, 1 paper enclosure
    - Journal fragment, 1806 Jul. 3-15; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 1-18)
      This fragment is written on different paper from that of any of the bound journals or notebooks. It includes the discovery of the pass later known as Lewis and Clark's. Lewis left pages 81-98 of Codex L blank for insertion of these pages.
      - Monture (Seaman's) Creek, Powell County, Montana, 1806 Jul. 5 (Page 4)
  - Codex Lb, 1 paper enclosure
    - Journal fragment, 1806 Aug. 9-12; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809 (Page 1-6)
      Lewis calls for this supplement in Codex L, p. 144.
  - Codex M, 1 volume